ELDIN SAHBAZ

Denver, Colorado, USA +1 (607) 597-9607 | sahbaz.eldin@gmail.com linkedin.com/in/eldinsahbaz | github.com/eldinsahbaz

SUMMARY

Program Manager and Data Scientist with 7+ years of proven success establishing and scaling transformative, enterprise-level, AI/ML initiatives across the Petroleum and Semiconductor industries. Led the Data Science team's 63% market share in AI developments across British Petroleum's US onshore O&G business and independently produced US\$50MM in value. Delivered patent-pending AI solutions in computational chemistry — valued at US\$500M+ annually — for INFICON's Semiconductor business.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Program Manager

British Petroleum (BP)

November 2023 – Present

Denver. Colorado

- · Directed and executed strategy for BP US onshore Data Science and ML Engineering achieving 47% market share in Exploration & Development and enabling the team's 63% market share across the division.
- · Managed and deployed the Long-term Production Risk Assessment Simulation tool for Reservoir Engineering.
- Oversaw the AWS migration for PowerBI reports monitoring the Productivity Index and Saltwater Disposal.

Senior Data Scientist

British Petroleum (BP)

February 2023 – Present

Denver. Colorado

- Generated US\$20MM annually in value for Reservoir Engineering's EOR initiatives delivering the ML Refracturing Estimator and increasing confidence in the Business Unit's Development program by 500%.
- Drove US\$30MM in formation evaluation cost reductions for the Bone Spring and the Wolfcamp launching ML Lithology Recognition for unconventional reservoirs in partnership with Subsurface Technology.

Data Scientist INFICON

June 2018 - February 2023 Syracuse, New York

· Directed the Automated Sensor Calibration development program for semiconductor sensor technologies delivering patent-pending advances driving annual cost reductions forecasted in excess of US\$500M.

- · Invented the Bijective Neural Architecture for density estimation yielding a 95% increase in accuracy.
- · Led efforts defining mathematical foundations for signal processing algorithms and designed A/B tests using SciPy.stats and Nolds — delivering a 21% increase in sensor fidelity using SciPy.optimize and Statsmodels.
- · Established KPIs and executed A/B tests with simulated chemical data via PySwarms, SciPy.optimize, SciPy.stats, and SciPy.integrate — attaining 50% coverage across chemical detection/monitoring systems.

PATENTS & PUBLICATIONS

Method of Auto Tuning One or More Sensors

February 2024

USPTO Application 18/686,753

Patent Pending

PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Core Analysis Workshop

April 2024/December 2023

UT Austin Bureau of Economic Geology

Advanced Power BI — Power Query and DAX

April 2023

Power BI — Reporting and Model Building February 2023 Havens Consulting Machine Learning for Model Predictive Control & Process Analytics June 2019 Dr. S. Joe Qin INVITED PRESENTATIONS Neural Attention for Seismic Data Processing July 2024 BP Geophysics R&D Seminar Improving Mass Spectrometry Signal Fidelity November 2020 INFICON Data Analytics Summit Introduction to AI and Machine Learning November 2020 INFICON Data Analytics Summit Automatic Text Summarization — Deep Learning & Classical Approaches April 2018 Syracuse University iSchool Poster Session **HONORS & AWARDS** Graduate Merit Scholarship August 2017 - May 2018 Syracuse University Summa Cum Laude May 2017 Syracuse University The Warren Semon Prize May 2017 Syracuse University Dean's Leadership Grant September 2014 Syracuse University Dean's List August 2014 – May 2017 Syracuse University The Founders' Scholarship August 2014 – May 2017 Syracuse University

EDUCATION

Syracuse University May 2018

Master of Science | Computer Science

Syracuse University

Bachelor of Science | Computer Science

Summa Cum Laude

SKILLS & COMPETENCIES

Software & Tools AWS SageMaker, Linux, Git, Python, PyTorch, Scikit-learn, Statsmodels, Pandas,

SciPy, NumPy, NLTK, Gensim, OpenCV, Seaborn, Matplotlib, SLB Techlog

Competency Areas AI, Deep Learning, Machine/Statistical Learning, Linear & Nonlinear Modeling, Numerical Optimization, Regression, Classification, Statistics, Probability, Time Series, Statistical Signal Processing, Data Analysis, Data Mining, Agile, CRISP-DM